# Michael B. Galarneau

19 Karens Way, Dover, NH 03820 ● mobile: (860) 614-0364 ● michael.qalarneau@comcast.net

# **Key Skills**

Digital Campaign Marketing

CRM & Contact Center Services

Complex System Architecture

HealthCare Insurance

Property & Casualty Insurance

Individual Life & **Annuities** 

Strategic Planning, Technical Roadmaps & Governance

Management of highly technical teams & projects

Written & Oral presentations to C-Level executives

# **Certifications &** Training

- UNH Full Stack Developer Bootcamp (March, 2019)
- Amazon Solution Architect Training
- Agile / Scaled Agile Framework
- TOGAF (certified)
- Lean 6 Sigma
- **PCI** Regulations

# **Education**

Central Connecticut State University, New Britain, CT

#### **BS** in Computer Science

- University Scholar
- Cum Laude

# ARCHITECTURE & DEVELOPMENT

Healthcare, Property & Casualty, Life Insurance & Annuities

Extensive experience in development, deployment and maintenance of technology solutions in the customer domain. Key results include digital marketing solutions to drive increased customer engagement and net promoter scores while simultaneously reducing operational expenses.

Twenty years in the financial sector with understanding of complex insurance products for healthcare, property and life & annuity domains. Versatile across broad spectrum of technology and business solutions with experience driving application development and architecture solutions, in both leadership and senior contributor roles.

# Technology Summary

Languages	JavaScript, HTM	IL/CSS, NodeJ	S, Java J2EE	, C/C++, SQL
-----------	-----------------	---------------	--------------	--------------

**Platforms** Teradata CIM/RTIM, Eloqua, Salesforce.com, Knowledge Management

**Database** IBM DB2/UDB, Microsoft SQLSever, MySQL

**Oper Systems** Amazon AWS, Unix, Linux, Windows

Identity & Access Management, Federation, RBAC, LDAP/AD Security

**Tooling** Sparx Enterprise Architect, MSViso, Git, Confluence

IT Policies & Change & Configuration Management, Project Management, Quality Assurance, Release Management, Architecture, DR/COB, Information **Processes** 

Security & Compliance, Cloud Computing & Service Automation

## **Experience Summary**

Cigna Healthcare, Bloomfield, CT	2012-preent
Director / Principal Architect Ciana Global Architecture	

Director / Principal Architect, Cigna Global Architecture

**IBM Corporation**, Bedford, NH 2010-2012 Software Architect & Cloud Specialist

Liberty Mutual Insurance, Dover, NH 2005-2010

Director Architecture & Security Market Architect - Personal Markets

Citigroup - Travelers Life & Annuity, Hartford, CT 2003-2005

Director of Architecture, Lead Architect

Lincoln Financial Group, Hartford, CT 1995-2003

Lead Architect - Individual Life Manager, Application Architecture

Software Consulting, Bloomfield, CT 1992-1995

Sr. Systems Consultant

Aetna Individual Insurance, Corporate Tax Systems

ABB-Combustion Engineering, Instrumentation & Controls, Nuclear Systems

Gerber Scientific, Tolland, CT 1988-1992

Software Engineer

Michael B. Galarneau Page 2

## Cigna Healthcare (Current Role)

**Digital Marketing**: Creating a next generation data management platform to drive analytics to micro target a population and develop personalized campaigns to create the proverbial "segment of one" experience.

Directly contributed to the architecture and delivery of Cigna's enterprise CRM campaign management solution delivering realtime, batch and online next best actions for omni-channel customer engagement solution.

**Agile Engineering**: Fully versed in agile development process with DevOps methodologies in small team and enterprise scale (scaled-agile) to delivery agile solutions in a complex integrated environment (where appropriate).

✓ Provide architecture direction, guidance and solutions in a combined business and technical teams.

#### **IBM**

**Security**: Provide technical consulting of Tivoli's comprehensive security portfolio. Engagements include briefings, detailed product demos, technical deep dives, written RFI/RFP/RFQs and technical proof of concepts.

✓ Directly contributed to the closing of software and services sales for identity & access management, federation and virtual directory services engagements.

**Cloud**: Versed in self-service portals, service catalogs & offerings, workflow, provisioning, monitoring & accounting in X-series and P-series virtual environments.

✓ Provide education, briefings, demos, consulting on infrastructure and software as a service initiatives.

#### **Liberty Mutual**

**Auto & Property - Services Refactoring**: Chartered comprehensive overhaul of services platform supporting auto and property.

✓ Met or exceeded key measures despite business growth 2-3x industry average. Re-platform effort involved move from C++ to IBM Process Server architecture and platform virtualization.

**Information Security – PCI/NPPI Assessment & Enclave**: Assessed and implemented strategic solution to secure sensitive cardholder data and other non-public personal information to meet "board level" scrutiny.

✓ Results included complete architecture and operational solution tokenizing pci data to reduce real risk profile, pass internal and external audits with no impact to cash processing operations and availability.

**Architecture – Strategic Roadmap & Retirements**: Chartered multi-disciplined business and IT strategic roadmapping effort in coordination with strategic consulting partner.

✓ Implemented multi-year plan for aligning business and technology initiatives with detail action plan and tooling to keep it "fresh". Strategic roadmap was foundation for services refactoring effort.

**Information Security - Identity Management**: Developed and implemented repeatable tooling processes and controls to monitor and track use of system and user IDs across all systems and environments.

✓ Resulted in detailed inventory, processes and procedures to manage thousands of IDs to ensure accountability, reduced risk, reduced maintenance costs and audit compliance.

**Architecture Governance:** Implemented architecture and security governance practices into project and portfolio management process. Process includes gap assessments to planned roadmaps and disciplines to ensure solution patterns are developed replacing history of ad-hoc development processes.

✓ Reduced architectural complexity (16 layers down to 4), reduced failure points and increased availability.

### **Travelers Life & Annuity**

- Completed technical strategy with expense management and cost reduction being primary business driver.
- Implemented wholesaler effectiveness initiative to integrate data warehouse and new business systems with salesforce.com and Blackberry devices (Vettro application)

#### **Lincoln Financial**

- Architected and developed in-house illustration platform for complete line of insurance products providing ability to use internal or external vendors as well as desktop or web-enabled applications.
- Personally implemented UL/SUL, VUL/SVUL, fixed and variable annuity products, including patent pending algorithm for universal life long term guarantees.

#### **ABB-Combustion Engineering**

• Developed "fixed panel display builder" application for Nuplex 2000 nuclear reactor, a meta-screen builder that allows for customization of control room screens without code recompiling or redeployment.

# **Gerber Garment Technology**

• Developed real-time embedded factory automation platforms at kernel and device driver level. Wrote complex sorting algorithm for made-to-measure shops and triaged hardware level issues in 8, 16 and 32 bit architecture.

Able to travel domestically or internationally • Available for full-time & contract assignments